A Guide to the Lewis G. Longsworth papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA177
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lewis G. Longsworth papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1930-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Longsworth, Lewis G.
FA177
5 Cubic Feet 17 boxes and 2 volumes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Date received or inventoried: February, 1975.
Biographical/Historical note
Lewis Gibson Longsworth, researcher in physical chemistry at The Rockefeller University from 1930 until his retirement in 1970 with researches and publications on the electrochemistry of salt and protein solutions with applications in biology and medicine. His major interest has been in the determination of mobilities, first of small ions, then of macromolecules such as protein and finally of uncharged particles that do not respond to an electric field.
Biographical note
1904 Born November 16 in Somerset, Kentucky
1925 A. B. Southwestern College, Winfield, Kansas
1927 M. A. Kansas University, Lawrence, Kansas
1928 Ph. D. Kansas University, Lawrence, Kansas
1928-1930 National Research Council Fellow at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York City
1930-1939 Assistant in Physical Chemistry, RIMR, New York City
1939-1945 Associate in Physical Chemistry, RIMR, N. Y. C.
1945-1949 Associate Member, RIMR, N. Y. C.
1949-1970 Member and Professor, Rockefeller University, N. Y. C.
1963 Moundbuilder Citation for Distinguished Service Southwestern College
1968 American Chemical Society Award in Chromatography and Electrophoresis
1970- Professor Emeritus, The Rockefeller University (Closed laboratory)
Served: Civilian investigator on Manhattan Project OSRD 1941-1942, Editorial Boards of: Journal of The American Chemical Society; Journal of General Physiology; Journal of Colloid Science, National Academy of Sciences: Committee oh Battery and Additives, 1953-1961; Committee to Evaluate a Classified Project of Bureau of Ships, 1962
Member of: National Academy of Sciences, New York Academy of Science (Vice-president 1944), American Chemical Society, Electrochemical Society, Harvey Society, Sigma Xi, Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha Chi Sigma
Scope and Contents note
Professional correspondence, collected reprints, slides, and other special formats (transparencies, prints, illustrations, and negatives).
Boxes 1 and 2 consist of biographical material, bibliography and collected reprints. Primarily a collection of professional correspondence (1935-1969). Correspondence consists of exchanges of scientific information, discussions of problems and suggested approaches for design and use of apparatus; discussion of experimental results and calculations. Includes frequent examples of detailed analyses and calculations to assist in the experimental work, calculation or interpretation of diffusion and electrophoretic work done in other laboratories or other investigators. Some correspondence deals with arrangements for conferences.
Box 3 contains slides. Boxes 4-17 contain slides and other special formats (transparencies, prints, illustrations, and negatives).
Arrangement note
Boxes 1 and 2 are arranged in alphabetical and chronological order. Correspondence arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent. The number of items is shown by figure in parentheses.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 L866
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biology -- Research; Electrophoresis; Medical technology; Medical sciences; Medical research; Electrochemistry; Chemistry; Biochemistry; Life sciences; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Biographical material, 1
  Arrangement
  Boxes 1 and 2 are arranged in alphabetical and chronological order.
  - Biographical sketch prepared by Lewis G. Longsworth (Box 1)
  - Biographical sketch prepared by University Public Relations (Box 1)
  - Bibliography (Box 1)
  - Citation from Office of Scientific Research and Development (photocopy), 1945 March 1 (Box 1)
  - Patent 2,563,729 (photocopy), 1951 August 7 (Box 1)
  - 2 photographs (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 2
  Correspondence arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent.
  - A (Box 1)
    - Alberty, Robert A., 1945-1960
    - Abramson, Harold A., 4 letters
    - Afghan, B. K., 2 items
    - Agar, John N., 24 items
    - Ahrens, E. H., 2 items
    - Amis, Edward S., 2 items
    - Angers, John W., 1 item
    - Appel, F. W., 2 items
    - Archibald, R. M., 2 items
    - Ashton, J. M., 1 item
    - Astin, A. V., 1951-1955; 25 items
      Scope and Contents note
      Chairman of Committee on Tables of Constants and numerical data.
      Includes correspondents R. C. Gibbs and W. Albert Noyes.
      Includes also, copies of meetings minutes and progress reports.
    - Austrian, S., 2 items
  - B (Box 1)
    - Babb, A. L., 3 items
    - Baldwin, R. L., 2 items
    - Baskin, Leonard S., 5 items
    - Bass, Lawrence W. Meeting of New York section of American Chemical Society, 1936 May 8; 4 items
    - Bates, Roger G. Congratulations on ACS Award in Chromatography, 1968; 1 item
    - Bearman, Richard J., 10 items
    - Beckman, Charles O. Columbia University Colloquium, 1957 November 6; 2 items
    - Becsey, Julius, 3 items
      Includes photos and drawings on investigations.
    - Beyerlein, Adolph On mss "Thermogravitational Thermal Diffusion V...", 3 items
    - Bier, Milan Introduction to v. 2 of Electrophoresis, 8 items
    - Bierlein, James A., 1958; 21 items
      Includes recommendation in 1958 for NSF fellowship grant.
    - Brattsten, Inger, 2 items
    - Briggs, Lyman J., 8 items
    - Brink, Frank Reports on RI graduate students, 1964-1966; 21 items
    - Bryngdahl, Olof, 1 item
    - Buff, Frank P., 2 items
    - Bull, Henry B. On review of mss "The Effective Electrophoretic Radii of adsorbed protein molecules", 2 items
    - Burt-Gerrans, J. S., 2 items
    - Butler, J. A. V., 3 items
  - C (Box 1)
    - Cann, John R., 1949-1961; 10 items
    - Cannon, R. Keith, 1939-1947; 31 items
      Primarily concerned with work on egg albumin; includes some items on protein conference, New York Academy of Sciences 1940 Nov. 8-9.
    - Chanu, J. K.
    - Claesson, Stig, 2 items
      Includes 2 photographs.
    - Cohn, Edwin J., 2 items
    - Coryell, Charles D., 2 items
    - Creeth, J. Michael, 11 items
    - Curtis, Raymond M. Electrophoretic studies on maternal and fetal plasma, 1941-1944; 25 items
  - D-E-F (Box 1)
    - Davidson, Arthur W. letter of appreciation and good wishes, 1966; 3 items
      Includes letters to Clarke Weskoe, Ernest Griswald.
    - Davies, J. A., 2 items
      Includes two graphs on diffusion coefficients.
    - Doty, Paul, 2 items
    - Dunlop, Peter J., 8 items
    - Eisenman, George, 3 items
    - Eldredge, Noreen Problems of a satisfactory diffusion cell, 2 items
    - Eliassaf, J. Diffusion data of some salts at elevated temperatures, 2 items
    - Farrar, John advice on optical system apparatus, 2 items
    - Feakins, D., 3 items
    - Ferry, Ronald M., 15 items
    - Fischer, L., 3 items
    - Fox, Malcolm F., 2 items
    - French, Dexter Diffusion measurements on cyclohepta-amylose, 1 item
    - Fuoss, Raymond M., 4 items
    - Fricke, Hugo Conduction measurements on bacteria, 1 item
  - Gibson-Gordon (Box 1)
    - Gibson, R. E. letter of appreciation for work as a Referee for National Academy of Sciences Research Council Committee in Basic Research, Advisory to Office of Ordnance Research for U.S. Army, 1959
    - Gilbert, G. A. Moving boundary theory applications; "bimodal" boundary, 12 items
    - Gordon, A. R., 1942-1953; 19 items
      Includes copy of mss submitted to Journal of American Chemical Society, 1953.
  - Gosting (Box 1)
    - Gosting, Louis J., 1947-1959; circa 1 inch
      Biographical/Historical note
      National Research Council Fellow in MacInnes Lab September 1948-June 1950
  - H-I-J (Box 1)
    - Haase, R., 4 items
    - Halwer, Murrav, 2 items
    - Hartley, G. S., 5 items
    - Heidelberger, M. Results of electrophoretic analyses of ovalbumin preparations, 1 item
    - Helmer, Oscar M., 2 items
    - Hoch, Hans, 2 items
    - Huddleson, I. Forest, 4 items
    - Huffman, E. O., 4 items
    - Irwin, M. R. Differentiation work between serum proteins and hemoglobins of horse, mule and donkey, 2 items
    - Jacobsen, C. F. Six month visitor in laboratory 1947-1948, 7 items
    - James, G. Watson, 3 items
  - K (Box 1)
    - Kauzmann, Walter J., 4 items
    - Kedem, Orah, 6 items
    - Kegeles, Gerson, 17 items
    - Kirkwood, John G., 3 items
    - Klotz, I. M. Diffusion of hemerythrin, 8 items
    - Krause, C. A. Congratulations on 90th birthday, 1 item
    - Krucke, E., 4 items
  - L-M (Box 1)
    - La Mer, Victor, 4 items
    - Lamm, O., 2 items
    - Li, C. H., 4 items
    - Linderstrøm-Lang, K. 6-month visit of Jacobsen to Lab. Analysis, micro-photo and copy of publication note on new protein derived from ovalbumin called plakalbumin, 11 items
    - Lippman, Richard W., 2 items
    - Lyons, Philip A., 13 items
      Includes items from and about Arthur D. Payton.
    - McMeekin, Thomas L. from U.S. Dept of Agriculture, 2 items
    - Martin, A. J. P., 3 items
    - Meleny, Frank, 1 item
    - Metcalf, W. S., 2 items
    - Meyer, Karl, 1 item
    - Miller, Donald G. Diffusion experiment readings on AgNO₃, 4 items
    - Mudge, C. S., 3 items
    - Muntz, John A., 2 items
  - N (Box 2)
    - Neurath, Hans, 1941-1965; 53 items
    - Nobel Committee for Chemistry. Nomination of Lyman C. Craig, 1952-1960; 11 items
    - Northrop, John H. Question of homogeneity of a purified antitoxin, 1941; 4 items
  - O (Box 2)
    - Ogston, A. G. The Gouy Diffusionmeter, 3 items
    - Oncley, J. L., 14 items
    - Onsager, Lars, 10 items
    - Oster, Gerald, 5 items
      Includes one holograph and 2 diffusion photos.
    - Osterhout, W. J. V. Primarily holograph letters on mss, but includes several personal items, 21 items
  - P (Box 2)
    - Payton, Arthur see under Lyons, Philip A.
    - Pembroke, Richard H. Electrophoretic patterns of maternal and fetal plasma, 11 items
    - Perera, George A. Tiselius pattern used in diagnostic confirmation, 4 items
    - Perlmann, Gertrude E., 1943-1952; 21 items
    - Phillips, Hannah, 4 items
    - Plotz, Harry Electrophoretic analysis of typhus vaccine supernate, 5 items
    - Poison, A., 2 items
    - Putnam, Frank W. Elecrophoretic study of a water soluble fraction of a naturally occurring mixture of plant proteins, 2 items
  - R-S (Box 2)
    - Rhodes, E., 2 items
    - Rivers, T. M. Use of electrophoretic patterns to distinguish between whole and reconstituted milk, 1 item
    - Rockefeller Institute Deals with various graduate students and materials for physical chemistry teaching and examination, 1964-1966; 17 items
    - Scatchard, George, 6 items
    - Schachman, Howard K., 3 items
    - Scheraga, H. A., 10 items
    - Schonert, Hansjurgen, 5 items
    - Scudder, John Electrophoretic patterns of Dr. Elliot's serum and plasma samples, 1 item
    - Sendroy, Julius Apparatus for electrophoretic measurements, 2 items
    - Sitharama Rao, D. N. On thesis review, 9 items
      Includes 7 items with R. H. Stokes and Registrar of Univ. of Poona.
    - Smith, Edgar Reynolds, 1942-1956; 12 items
    - Smithies, O., 2 items
    - Snell, Fred M., 3 items
    - Solomon, A. K., 2 items
    - Squire, Phil G., 2 items
    - Steele, J. Murray, 3 items
    - Steigman, Joseph, 2 items
    - Stockmayer, Walter H., 1951; 5 items
      Includes 1951 mss "Theory of moving concentration boundaries".
    - Stokes, R. H., 8 items
      Includes thesis review for B. J. Steel see also Sitharama Rao on thesis review.
    - Stoll, Norman, 2 items
    - Strohl, C. Orville Moundbuilder Citation for Distinguished Service from Southwestern College, 4 items
      Includes acceptance remarks.
    - Sturtevant, Julian M., 2 items
    - Svensson, Harry, 1939-1955; 35 items
  - T-Z (Box 2)
    - Tanner, C. C., 2 items
    - Tiselius, Arne, 7 items
    - Trautman, Rodes, 1962; 4 items
      Includes Longsworth mss "Experimental Procedures suggested by a comparison of Short-Column Sedimentation by Thermal Diffusion" 1962 Colloid Symposium.
    - Tyrrell, H. J. V., 7 items
    - Van Holde, K. E. on sealing Tiselius cells, 2 items
    - Villegas, Raimundo Assistance with diffusion coefficients of some solutes in water solution, 5 items
    - Wales, Michael Comments on report of Ultracentrifuge Conference, 1950; 3 items
    - Wang, Jui H., 1 item
    - Weeks, Sinclair 1954 letter of appreciation for work and report of National Academy of Sciences Committee on Battery, 1 item
    - Williams, J. W. Testing of Gerson Kegeles theory of interference fringes at schlieren diaphragm, 2 items
    - Wishnia, Arnold Discussion of possible effects of charge fluctuation on reversible boundary spreading, 2 items
    - Young, E. Gordon, 2 items
- Slides and other Special Formats, 3
  - Slides, 2½" ms. box (Box 3)
    Arrangement note
    Original slide groupings, by number.
    0-99 Activities, 0-49 Apparatus, 50-99 Measurements, 100-199 Bacteriology, 100-149 Apparatus, 150-199 Measurements, 200-299 Conductance, 200-249 Apparatus, 200-224 Cells, 225-249 Circuits, 250-299 Measurements, 300-399 Differential Titrations, 300-349 Apparatus, 350-399 Measurements, 400-449 Distribution Ratios, 500-599 Glass Electrode, 600-699 Ionization Constants, 700-799 Liquid Junctions, 700-724 Apparatus, 724-774 Theory, 774-799 Observations, 800-899 Optical Properties, Inc., 900-999 Overvoltage, 1000-1099 Pressure Effect on E.M.F., 1100-1199 Transference Numbers, 1100-1124 Apparatus, 1125-1149 Theory, 1159-1199 Measurements, 1200-1299 Heavy Water, 1200-1249 Apparatus, 1250-1299 Measurements, 1300-1399 Electrophoresis, 1300-1309 Apparatus, 1310-1319 Methods, 1320-1349 Diagrams, Patterns, 1350-1359 Mobilities, 1360-1369 Quantitative, 1360-1369 Quantitative Interpretation of Patterns, 1380-1389 Vaccine Virus, 1420-1430 Sedimentation, 1500 Solubility, 1600-1699 Miscellaneous, 1700-1739 Electron Microscope, 1740-1780 EMF Centrifuge, 1800 Galvanic Cell, 1900-1910 Concentration Boundaries, 1911-1920 Moving Boundary Systems, 1921-1930 Moving Boundaries of Weak Electrolytes, 1951-1959 Two-Salt Boundaries, 1960-1969 Binding of Salt Ions by Proteins, 1970 Differential Ionic Hydration, 2000 Interference Method for the Study of Diffusion, 2000-2010 Method, 2020 Interference Fringe Photo, 2030 Optical Methods, 2040-2049 Diffusion Cells, 2050-2059 Diffusion Results, 2100 Magnetic Float Method, [No number] Diffusion Res.
    Explanatory note by CK 12 Jan 1984:
    The original order of these slides was lost during the clean-up after the flood [Note: 22 Dec. 1982]. They were re-grouped into the following categories:
    A Recordings and Tracings
    B Tables
    C Drawings
    D Graphs
    E Photographs [apparatus]
    Scope and Contents
    [xx] is used within this series in the finding aid to refer to diagrams in the original paper finding aid. Please see the archivist to obtain a paper copy of the finding aid.
    - Recordings and Tracings, A; Glass slides (Box 3)
      - [Bars with handwritten labels], 1961 March 9; A1
      - Tracing [xx], A2
      - Tracing [xx], A3
      - 61-1680B, A4
      - Recording, thin bands [xx], A5
      - Recordings a-j 2400-1600 seconds, A6
      - Schlieren scanning patterns of 1.5% raffinose boundaries in 0.1 N LiCl, A7
      - 1.5% raffinose boundaries in 0.1 N LiCl [1904], A8
      - Fig. 7 Tracings of the patterns obtained during the electrolysis of 0.2N: 0.5 N Solutions of potassium chloride., A9; Image
      - 0.1 N Na Acetate: 0.1 N NaCl, 0.1 N NaI [1915], A10
      - 0.2 N KI03: 0.15 N KI03, 0.05 N KC1 [1814], A11
      - Fig. 9 Tracings of the patterns obtained during the electrolysis of 0.1 N: 0.2 N solutions' of cadmium iodide, A12
      - [xx], A13
      - Vertical thin bands, A14
      - Diffusion of 0.4% digitonin in 63% ethanol, A15
    - Tables, B; Glass slides (Box 3)
      - Diffusion coefficients of iodine at zero concentration in some organic solvents at 25 deg, B1
      - Effect of temperature on the diffusion coefficients of some solutes at zero concentration in water, B2
      - Table 3: Results of moving boundary analyses of barium-calcium-magnesium mixtures. L. G. Longsworth 2853-7B, 1951 September 12; B3
      - Treatment of fringe data Pattern of 0.75% levulose after diffusion for 13003 seconds, B4
      - Table. 2. Results of moving boundary analyses of chloratebromate mixtures, B5
      - Effect of temperature on diffusion in dilute aqueous solutions C [unreadable] = 0.3 wt%, B6
    - Drawings, C; Glass slides (Box 3)
      - 0.1 normal KC1. MacInnes and Dole, C1
      - Milli-ammeter, Zn, Cu..., C2
      - Zn, H2, Potemtiometer, C3
      - 0.1 N CaCl2 0.2 N CaCl2, C4
      - Arrangement for determining the effect of gravity on the potential of a galvanic cell [1802], C5
      - - CuSO4 soln NaCl in agar soln. + traces BaCl2; NaOH, phenolphthalein H2SO4 soln. +, C6
      - H2SO4 H2SO4 HNO3... [1801], C7
      - n1=2 n2 D1=4D2... n1=2 n2 D1=1/4 D2..., C8
      - Apparatus outline: [xx], C9
      - (SO4) (current) [—— (H), C10
      - Horizontal lengths drawn to scale [xx], C11
    - Graphs, D; Glass slides (Box 3)
      - Pressure x Overvoltage, D1
      - Seconds x Overvoltage, D2
      - Mean relative concn. x Normalized fringe separation, D3
      - Vh / 2kuc × 2kuc / vC1 dn / dh, D4
      - Pressure x Overvoltage for a platinum electrode, D5
      - Concn. × Dx 106, D6
      - Comparator reading-cm. x Fringe number, D7
      - Fig. 5 Transference numbers of lanthanum chloride as a function of the square roots of the concentration: +, Jones and Prendergast: ● direct, moving boundary method; O, differential moving boundary method, D8
      - Mean relative concn. x Normalised fringe separation, D9
    - Photographs, E; Glass slides (Box 3)
      - glass apparatus, E1
      - Apparatus, Dr. Ecker C-37466 XI-13-47, E2
      - Apparatus A-37466 XI-13-47, E3
      - Apparatus D-37466 XI-13-47, E4
      - [2043] Apparatus, E5
      - [2041] 37268C-B Longsworth Apparatus, E6
      - [2042] A-37268 Apparatus VI-4-47 Dr. Longsworth, E7
      - [2100] Apparatus, E8
    - Slides added (Box 3)
      - "Fig. 3 Human serum, myeloma. Migration time 38' at 8.3 V/cm. 5391-7D L. G. Longsworth 2 Mar 55", A16
      - L. G. Longsworth 7729-7 30 Dec 57, 1957 December 30; A17
      - "Drawing of a Volta Pile", C12
      - Fringe number × Diffusion coefficient × 10⁶, D10
      - [Console], E9
      - Drawing and recording: L. G. Longsworth 6923-7B Rev, 1957 January 8; F1
  - Slides and other special formats, Boxes 4-10 are 4x4 slide boxes.
    Contains slides and other special formats (transparencies, prints, illustrations, and negatives).
    - Cartons 1-3: Miscellaneous "A": recordings, tracings, patterns (Box 4)
      Conditions Governing Access
      RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
    - Carton-1: "A" (Recordings...) (Box 5)
    - Cartons 2-3: "B" Miscellaneous (Tables) (Box 5)
    - Carton 1: "B" Miscellaneous (Tables) (Box 6)
    - Cartons 2-3: "C" Miscellaneous (Drawings) (Box 6)
    - Cartons 1-3: "C" Miscellaneous (Drawings) (Box 7)
    - Cartons 1-3: "D" Miscellaneous (Graphs) (Box 8)
    - Cartons 1-3: "D" Miscellaneous (Graphs) (Box 9)
    - Carton 1: "E" Miscellaneous (Photos, primarily of apparatus, some of microorganisms) (Box 10)
    - Carton 2: "F" Miscellaneous (3 2-part slides) (Box 10)
    - Carton 3: "G" Miscellaneous (Equations) (Box 10)
    - Color transparencies Original cards used as dividers, in wood slide trays. [See previous page for transcript], 2½ × 6 in. ms box (Box 11)
    - Black and white prints (curling) of virus and apparatus, 2½ × 8 in. ms box (Box 12)
    - Illustrations - includes charts, diagrams, and graphs, 2½" ms box (Box 13)
    - Lantern slides and photographic negatives - microorganisms (Box 14)
    - Illustrations - includes charts, diagrams, graphs, and photographs (Box 15)
    - Illustrations - includes charts, diagrams, graphs, and photographs (Box 16)
    - Photographic negatives - miscellaneous scientific material (Box 17)
- Collected Reprints, 2 volumes